Sardana Ivanova

Kandidaatintie 1B 5, 02700 Kauniainen, Finland

Email: sardana.ivanova@helsinki.fi

Languages: Sakha (Native), Russian (Native), English (C1), Japanese (B2), Finnish (B1)¹

Profile

Doctoral researcher at the Department of Computer Science at the University of Helsinki and a visiting researcher in the Institute of Informatics at the University of Oslo. Passionate about language technology for lesser-resourced, indigenous and marginalised languages. Member of the Association of Computational Linguistics (ACL), Turkic Interlingua.

Education

Years	University	Title	Awarded
2019-Present	University of Helsinki	Computer Science	
2015-2017	North-Eastern Federal University (Yakutsk)	Information Technologies	2017, MSc
2011-2015	North-Eastern Federal University (Yakutsk)	Information Technologies	2015, BSc
2007-2012	North-Eastern Federal University (Yakutsk)	Japanese Language	2012, BA,MA

Positions held

Year	Organisation	Title	Location
2022-Present	University of Oslo	Visiting doctoral researcher	Oslo, Norway
2019-Present	University of Helsinki	Doctoral researcher	Helsinki, Finland
2017	North-Eastern Federal University	Laboratory supervisor	Yakutsk, Russia
2014–2015	Mytona LLC	C++ programmer	Yakutsk, Russia

Grants and awards

Grants

Year	Awarding body	Description	Duration
2018	Finnish National Agency for Education	EDUFI Fellowship for doctoral studies in the University of Helsinki, Finland	12 months
2016	University of the Arctic	North2North grant for exchange studies in the university of Helsinki, Finland	4 months
2016	Erasmus Mundus	Grant for exchange studies in the University of Groningen, The Nethderlands	5 months

¹These levels are approximate.

Honors and awards

Year	Awarding body	Description	Location
2017	North-Eastern Federal University	Sofia Sidorova's Governmental Scholarship	Yakutsk, Russia
2017 2016	North-Eastern Federal University Ultrahack	Master's diploma with Honors Ultrahack 2016 hackathon Health track winner	Yakutsk, Russia Helsinki, Finland
2015	North-Eastern Federal University	Bachelor's diploma with Honors	Yakutsk, Russia

Publications

The following is a list of my peer-reviewed workshop and conference publications. Publications marked with *emph* have been reviewed and accepted for publication.

Conference papers

- 6. **Ivanova**, **S.**, Washington J. N., and Tyers, F. M. (2022) "A Free/Open-Source Morphological Analyser and Generator for Sakha". *Proceedings of the 12th Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2022)*
- 5. Zosa, E., Pivovarova, L., Boggia, M. and **Ivanova**, **S.** (2022) "Multilingual Topic Labelling of News Topics using Ontological Mapping". *Advances in Information Retrieval. (ECIR 2022)*
- Mirzakhalov, J., Babu, A., Ataman, D., Kariev, S., Tyers, F. M., Abduraufov, O., Hajili, M., Ivanova, S., Khaytbaev, A., Laverghetta, A., Moydinboyev, B., Önal, E., Pulatova, S., Wahab, A., Fırat, O. and Chellappan, S. (2021) "A Large-Scale Study of Machine Translation in Turkic Languages". Proceedings of the 2021 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- 3. Mirzakhalov, J., Babu, A., Kunafin, A., Wahab, A., Moydinboyev, B., **Ivanova, S.**, Uzokova, M., Pulatova, S., Ataman, D., Kreutzer, J., Tyers, F. M., Fırat, O., Licato, J., and Chellappan, S. (2021) "Evaluating Multiway Multilingual NMT in the Turkic Languages". Proceedings of the Sixth Conference in Machine Translation (WMT20)
- 2. Katinskaia, A., **Ivanova, S.** and Yangarber, R. (2020) "Toward a Paradigm Shift in Collection of Learner Corpora". Proceedings of the 12th Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2020)
- 1. **Ivanova, S.**, Katinskaia, A. and Yangarber, R. (2019) "Tools for supporting language learning for Sakha". Proceedings of the 22nd Nordic Conference on Computational Linguistics (NoDaLiDa)

Workshop papers

- 3. **Ivanova**, **S.**, Tyers, F. M. and Washington, J. N. (2021) "A Prototype Free/Open-Source Morphological Analyser and Generator for Sakha". *5th Widening NLP (WiNLP2021) workshop*
- 2. Pimentel, T., Ryskina, M., Mielke, S. J., Wu, S., Chodroff, E., Leonard, B., Nicolai, G., Ate, Y. G., Khalifa, S., Habash, N., El-Khaissi, C., Goldman, O., Gasser, M., Lane, W., Coler, M., Oncevay, A., Montoya Samame, J. R., Silva Villegas, G. C., Ek, A., Bernardy, J-P., Shcherbakov, A., Bayyr-ool, A., Sheifer, K., Ganieva, S., Plugaryov, M., Klyachko, E., Salehi, A., Krizhanovsky, A., Krizhanovsky, N., Vania, C., Ivanova, S., Salchak, A., Straughn, C., Liu, Z., Washington, J., Ataman, D., Kieraś, W., Woliński, M., Suhardijanto, T., Stoehr, N., Nuriah, Z., Ratan, S., Tyers, F. M., Ponti, E. M., Aiton, G., Hatcher, R. J., Prud'hommeaux, E., Kumar, R., Hulden, M., Barta, B., Lakatos, D., Szolnok, G., Ács, J., Raj, M., Yarowsky, D., Cotterell, R., Ambridge, B. and Vylomova, E. (2021) "SIGMORPHON

2021 Shared Task on Morphological Reinflection: Generalization Across Languages". Proceedings of the 18th SIGMORPHON Workshop on Computational Research in Phonetics, Phonology, and Morphology

1. Katinskaia, A., **Ivanova, S.** and Yangarber, R. (2019) "Multiple Admissibility in Language Learning: Judging Grammaticality using Unlabeled Data". Proceedings of The 7th Workshop on Balto-Slavic Natural Language Processing

Reviewing

Workshops:

LoResMT Low-Resource Machine Translation workshop

Summer schools:

ProbAl Nordic Probabilistic AI School

Teaching

Teaching assistance

Year	Term	Description	Location	Duration
2021	Spring	Natural Language Processing	Helsinki, Finland	2 months

Teaching and mentoring

The following course I have organised or participated in teaching outside of specific academic programs:

Year	Description	Location	Duration
2021	Sakha language learning group	Helsinki, Finland	6 months

I have taken part in the Google Summer of Code as a mentor for Apertium machine translation platform in 2019. This involves mentoring and directing students working on three-month projects related to language technology over the summer.

I have also taken part in the Google Code-in as a mentor for Apertium in 2018 and 2019. This involves mentoring and directing school students working on various tasks related to language technology.

Other activities

Sakha language representative at Common Voice—crowdsourcing project started by Mozilla to create a free database for speech recognition software, 2021-2022.